[Music]
in 2019 the city will be constructing an
artificial reef as part of the Palm
Beach shoreline project this complements
the beach nourishment works that were
completed in 2017 where we saw a large
dredge delivering some pretty
spectacular sound rainbows to the shore
of Palm Beach the Palm Beach artificial
reef will be built using large rock
boulders weighing up to 8 tons each and
will be located approximately 270 meters
offshore from 19th Avenue it will be 160
metres long and up to 80 metres wide
which means it would almost cover the
Metricon stadium football field
the artificial reef at its highest point
will sit one and a half metres below the
average water level palm beach is one of
the Gold Coast's most vulnerable beaches
to the threat of coastal erosion many
swell events past and present have
resulted in the loss of Beach amenity
exposure of sea walls and threatened
homes and public infrastructure so how
will the reef help with combating
coastal erosion well here on the Gold
Coast sand naturally moves north along
the coast as a result of the predominant
southeasterly wave direction this
innovative underwater structure will
influence the surrounding waves and
currents to temporarily slow the
northern transport of sand around the
reef this will hold the additional sand
delivered through the previous beach
nourishment works for longer and promote
a long-term increase in sand along
vulnerable sections of Palm Beach
once the sand has moved beyond the reef
it will naturally continue to move up
the coast now here is the part that may
cause some confusion a lot of the
increase in sand will be located just
off shore and not necessarily always
visible to beach users but rest assured
this sand will act as a buffer to
protect Palm Beach from future erosion
events ensuring everyone can continue to
enjoy their beach experience while the
main purpose of the reef is the coastal
protection the city understands how
important surfing is to our culture and
life
surfing has been kept in mind when
designing the reef and under certain
swell conditions there is predicted to
be waves breaking on the reef suitable
for intermediate surfers so how do you
design a reef it's not just a simple
pile of rocks coastal engineering
projects of this nature are complex and
challenging the city has worked with a
team of world-class experts in coastal
engineering to develop the best possible
solutions specific to Palm Beach
significant investigation and effort has
gone into the design including computer
modeling wave tank testing and real-life
coastal data analysis some pretty
impressive marine construction vessels
will be used to build the artificial
reef between May and October in 2019 tug
boats and split hopper barges will
transport the rocks from Brisbane to
Palm Beach where they will be placed on
the seafloor a backhoe dredger will then
accurately move the rocks into position
using GPS technology to ensure the
structure is built to the specific
design while the reef has been built
there will be an exclusion zone around
the offshore construction area to keep
the public safe
our beaches are at greatest natural
asset and we are always working hard to
protect them the Palm Beach shoreline
project is part of the ocean beaches
strategy ensuring our beaches are clean
healthy safe and accessible now and into
the future
you